Okay, so in this video then I'm going to
give you some basic tips and pointers
about what to look out for on the PNP
exam, right on PNP exam questions,
and really what you should be practicing
as well when you are
taking practice exams.
Now, first of all, this first bullet point
here, learn to pick out keywords and
phrases, distract to the relevant
information and so and so forth.
The first big exam tip that
I want to give is you should
always train yourself to read
the very last sentence first.
In any question, start off by reading the
very last sentence, right?
That is the question.
Don't start off by reading the scenario.
Read the very last sentence first,
because that is the question.
Once you've read the question,
then start from there.
A lot of times, the entire
scenario, they've given
you, is completely
irrelevant to the question.
A lot of times it's what we call bait and
switch type questions, where the scenario
will lead you in one
direction, but then the
question has got nothing
to do with that scenario.
It completely switches direction,
right?
And if you're focused on the scenario,
you end up answering a question that you
think is being asked or
you hope was being asked,
not the actual question
that is being asked.
Right.
So always, always focus on the last
sentence first.
Focus on the question.
Look at the option choices.
There's generally four option choices.
But there may be more.
Sometimes you have these
choose two or choose three
type questions, but generally
it's four option choices.
Right.
And, you know, look at the option choice.
A lot of times you can answer the question
just based on that last sentence.
Now, of course, a lot of times, The scenario
is going to be very relevant, right?
A lot of times the question will be,
what should you do in this situation?
In which case, then you have to go back
and read the scenario.
But at least now your focus is on the
question.
So now when you go back and you read the
scenario, that scenario invariably is
going to have a lot of irrelevant
information, a lot of distractors.
So now it's a lot easier to pick out
keywords, phrases, and eliminate
irrelevant information
and distractors because
ultimately that is what you want to do.
Sometimes the entire question can just
hinge on one key word or one phrase.
So that's the key there.
Learn to read the very last sentence
first.
Train yourself to do that.
And that is especially
the case also when you
look at option choices
and they all look correct.
Every single one of these option choices
looks correct.
They all look good.
Or two of them, they look almost
identical.
Two of them are very, very good answers.
Which one do we choose?
You need to learn to pick out the best
option.
Which of these is the best one?
You need to learn to choose the best
option.
And so there might be just one
key word or one key phrase that
makes one option choice
better than another option choice.
So you need to learn that.
And the only way of learning that is by
going through question after question.
Also, when you're reading the question,
when you're reading the very last
sentence, beware of these little words
here.
A lot of times they're overlooked,
such as not next, least likely,
most likely, best, first, last,
except, like not.
You miss out the word not in a question.
That has completely changed the context of
the question.
And it's very, very easy to do,
right?
Especially when you're three hours into an
exam, two hours into an exam.
It's very, very easy to misread and,
you know, miss out the word not or read at
least likely as most likely and so and so
forth.
So again, pay special attention to that,
right?
Read your very last sentence first.
Then as you're reading that last sentence,
look out for these little kind of words.
Also, when you're looking at option
choices, a lot of times, in fact,
most of the time, it's just going to be a
process of elimination.
So one of the option
choices you can eliminate
is what we call non-substantive options.
So as a simple example, we have a question
on quality control.
One of the option choices says,
quality is really important.
What does that mean?
Quality is really important.
What does that really mean?
It doesn't have any
meaning to it, or rather
it doesn't have any real substance to it.
it.
It's too vague as to what it means.
If you see an option choice like that,
generally that's going
to be the wrong option.
The questions can be ambiguous.
The questions themselves can be quite
vague.
But the option choices are not going to be
The option choices are going to have some
kind of substance to it.
Now, some basic assumptions that you can
make.
Just some basic assumptions
as we're going through
the class and as you are
taking exam questions.
So for every exam question, unless the
question sits otherwise, the basic
assumption is that a project
manager, we're always
proactive, always taking
some kind of action.
So proactive means, I
mean, constant communication
with our team members
and our key stakeholders.
We're always apprised of what's going on
in the project and we're always
communicating to stakeholder in what's
going on in the project.
Proactive also means things like,
for example, if we find a risk,
we're doing something to either eliminate
that risk, reduce the impact of that risk,
right, we're trying to prevent issues from
occurring, we see a potential issue,
we're going to do something to make sure
that issue doesn't arise.
Or if an issue has arisen, if an issue has
occurred, not only are we fixing that
issue, but we're also making sure that
issue doesn't reoccur again.
So always, always proactive in that way.
So in that sense, then, if you have option
choices, right, when you're looking at
option choice, think, or
which of these are the best
option, right, you're looking
at two option choices.
Two of these look really
good, and we know it's
one of these two, which
one should I choose?
Look out for if one is proactive and one
is reactive.
The proactive approach is
always going to be the best
option, right, rather than
the reactive approach.
You don't want to take an action after the
fact, you want to take it before the fact.
So proactive then would always be the best
option.
Also look out for options where it's
engaging stakeholders.
Project managers are always engaging
stakeholders.
That is a number one success factor on a
project.
One of the main reasons why you hire a
project manager to engage stakeholders.
All your stakeholders, and we're going to
talk about who's stakeholders are,
but all of your stakeholders,
a project manager, needs
to engage and motivate
all of their stakeholders.
So again, when you're looking at option
choices, you're trying to decide which is
the best one, look out for, which of these
is engaging the stakeholder the most.
Project managers always
do what's best for the
project, not necessarily
what's best for them.
So whenever you are managing a project,
whenever you're making a decision, Right.
And again, we're talking about the exam
questions here, right?
So again, always kind of look out for
those scenarios.
Project managers are going
to do whatever is best for
the project, not necessarily
what's best for them.
Now also, PMI, a real stickler for
documentation.
So you always assume
that adequate documentation
is constantly being performed, right?
We're constantly, constantly updating
documents.
Along with this also, change control.
PMI are actually a stickler for change
control as well.
So you always assume
that there is an adequate
change control process in place as well.
Again, always unless the question states
otherwise.
Now, some other assumptions here,
right?
Historical information is always
available.
Historical information on prior projects,
right?
So it's available and you can utilize that
historical information.
So again, you know, some of these
assumptions might not be in line with what
you might be used to at, you know,
in your line of work.
But remember, we are talking about the PMP
exam.
We are talking about PMI standards.
We're talking about PMI's principles.
So you have to answer
the question based on
their principles, based
on their standards.
So you always assume historical
information is always available.
Right.
Now, you already mentioned this just now.
Change control process is in place and is
being followed.
PMI, a real stickler about that.
You're always trying to prevent
scope, creep, goalplating,
you're properly controlling
all the work on the project.
You're properly controlling any changes on
the project.
So you have an adequate change control
process.
All right.
Now, when you see questions
from procurement, right,
procurement questions generally
from the buyer's perspective.
We'll talk about that in the procurement
management section.
Right.
But again, that's a basic assumption that
you're going to be making.
Generally, when you're looking at option
choices, right, if you see a negative
tone, somewhere in an option choice,
right?
You know, you're finger
pointing, blaming someone
else type of thing, you're
some kind of negative tone.
Generally, that's going to be an incorrect
option as well, right?
Because, again, you want to engage.
Collaboration is the key.
I want to collaborate with your
stakeholders.
You want to collaborate with team members.
You found an issue.
You want to fix that issue.
You don't want to start pointing fingers,
blaming anyone.
And then, again, what I just said,
collaboration.
You're always focused on collaborating
with team members and stakeholders.
All right.
Now, just some other basic exam tips.
What's written in red here is very,
very important.
Forget about your real world experiences.
Whatever you have learned
about project management,
you have to put that at
the back of your mind.
You almost have to unlearn everything you
have learned about project management.
And simply because, remember, every
industry manages projects differently.
There's no right or wrong way of managing
a project.
An IT project is managed very differently
to a construction project.
And then we have predictive projects and
agile projects.
Two very, very different ways of managing
projects altogether.
All PMI are doing here is they are
basically creating standards and
principles across all different types of
projects.
So you might not have
had experience of agile, or
you might not have had
experience of predictive.
So don't try to translate your world into
the PMI world.
Don't try, and when you're
answering a question, don't
try to answer the question
based on your experience.
You have to answer the
question based on PMI's
standards, based on
PMI's principles, right?
Because like I said, PMI are creating
standards and principles, right,
a generic standard that could be, utilized
across all industries, all projects.
So PMI standards are meant to support all
projects in all industries.
So remember that a project
in one industry is managed
very differently to a
project in another industry.
So you always have
to think in terms of PMI
standards when you
are answering a question.
And then also, you know, as
you're answering questions,
eliminate incorrect
answers, right, obviously.
Now a lot of times when you're looking at
option choices, you look at all options,
all four options, they all look good.
You need to learn to pick out the best
option.
Right.
You need to pick out keywords.
However, in the same token, you're going
to come across situations where you look
at all four of these options, all of the
options, and none of them are any good.
They're all no good, no good options.
None of these are any good.
Well, these are all incorrect.
Well, out of these no good options?
Which is the best one?
You have to choose the
best out of these no good
options, which is the least
worst out of these options.
So, again, you always have to watch out
for that.
One keyword, one key
phrase may make one option
choice better than
the other option choice.
And you have to practice all of that.
And sometimes, it's just
a case, simple solution
is correct, is sometimes the correct one.
Sometimes you'll come across an option
choice or an answer, a question,
it looks really obvious.
And then you might start second guessing
yourself.
Well, what's the catch here?
No, sometimes the simplest solution will
be the correct one.
Never, never leave a question blank.
There's no negative marking.
If you have to guess, then guess.
But never leave a question blank.